<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rgo on Jonathan Weisberg</title>
    <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/tags/rgo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rgo on Jonathan Weisberg</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 10:44:10 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jonathanweisberg.org/tags/rgo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Editorial Gravity</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/editorial-gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 10:44:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/editorial-gravity/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ve all been there. One referee is positive, the other negative, and the editor decides to reject the submission.
I&amp;rsquo;ve heard it said editors tend to be conservative given the recommendations of their referees. And that jibes with my experience as an author.
So is there anything to it&amp;mdash;is &amp;ldquo;editorial gravity&amp;rdquo; a real thing? And if it is, how strong is its pull? Is there some magic function editors use to compute their decision based on the referees&amp;rsquo; recommendations?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender &amp; Journal Referees</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/referee-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 09:34:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/referee-gender/</guid>
      <description>We looked at author gender in a previous post, today let&amp;rsquo;s consider referees. Does their gender have any predictive value?
Once again our discussion only covers men and women because we don&amp;rsquo;t have the data to support a deeper analysis.1
Using data from Ergo, we&amp;rsquo;ll consider the following questions:
 Requests. How are requests to referee distributed between men and women? Are men more likely to be invited, for example?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Defense of Reviewer 2</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/reviewer-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 10:36:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/reviewer-2/</guid>
      <description>Spare a thought for Reviewer 2, that much-maligned shade of academe. There&amp;rsquo;s even a hashtag dedicated to the joke:
A rare glimpse of reviewer 2, seen here in their natural habitat pic.twitter.com/lpT1BVhDCX
&amp;mdash; Aidan McGlynn (@AidanMcGlynn) January 15, 2017 
But is it just a joke? Order could easily matter here.
Referees invited later weren&amp;rsquo;t the editor&amp;rsquo;s first choice, after all. Maybe they&amp;rsquo;re less competent, less likely to appreciate your brilliant insights as an author.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender &amp; Journal Submissions</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/author-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 10:36:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/author-gender/</guid>
      <description>Does an author&amp;rsquo;s gender affect the fate of their submission to an academic journal? It&amp;rsquo;s a big question, even if we restrict ourselves to philosophy journals.
But we can make a start by using Ergo as one data-point. I&amp;rsquo;ll examine two questions:
 Question 1: Does gender affect the decision rendered at Ergo? Are men more likely to have their papers accepted, for example?
 Question 2: Does gender affect time-to-decision at Ergo?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Thursday Conundrum</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/the-thursday-conundrum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 10:14:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/the-thursday-conundrum/</guid>
      <description>In an earlier post we saw that Mondays and Thursdays are good for editors, at least at Ergo. Potential referees say yes more often when invited on these days. But why?
Mondays aren&amp;rsquo;t too puzzling. It&amp;rsquo;s the start of a new week, so people are fresh, and maybe just a little deluded about how productive the coming week will prove to be.
But Thursdays? They don&amp;rsquo;t seem especially special. I tried speculating a priori about what might be going on there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Editor&#39;s Favourite Days of the Week</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/an-editors-favourite-days/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 10:13:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/an-editors-favourite-days/</guid>
      <description>Finding willing referees is one of the biggest challenges for a journal editor. Are referees more willing some days of the week than others? Apparently they are, on Mondays&amp;hellip; and Thursdays, for some reason. At least, that&amp;rsquo;s how things have gone at Ergo the last couple years (2015 and 2016).
Data Consider the &amp;ldquo;bounce rate&amp;rdquo; for a given day of the week: the portion of invites sent on that day that end up being declined (bounce rate = #declined / #invited).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>