<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Jonathan Weisberg</title>
    <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Jonathan Weisberg</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 15:21:42 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Mosteller Hall Puzzle</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/teaching-monty-hall/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 15:21:42 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/teaching-monty-hall/</guid>
      <description>One of my favourite probability puzzles to teach is a close cousin of the Monty Hall problem. Originally from a 1965 book by Frederick Mosteller,1 here&amp;rsquo;s my formulation:
 Three prisoners, A, B, and C, are condemned to die in the morning. But the king decides in the night to pardon one of them. He makes his choice at random and communicates it to the guard, who is sworn to secrecy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy for Dummies, Part 7: Dominance</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-7---brier-dominance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-7---brier-dominance/</guid>
      <description>In our last two posts we established two key facts:
 The set of possible probability assignments is convex. Convex sets are &amp;ldquo;obtuse&amp;rdquo;. Given a point outside a convex set, there&amp;rsquo;s a point inside that forms a right-or-obtuse angle with any third point in the set.  Today we&amp;rsquo;re putting them together to get the central result of the accuracy framework, the Brier dominance theorem. We&amp;rsquo;ll show that a non-probabilistic credence assignment is always &amp;ldquo;Brier dominated&amp;rdquo; by some probabilistic one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journal Submission Rates by Gender: A Look at the APA/BPA Data</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/a-look-at-the-apa-bpa-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 11:45:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/a-look-at-the-apa-bpa-data/</guid>
      <description>Update: editors at CJP and Phil Quarterly have kindly shared some important, additional information. See the edit below for details.
A new paper on the representation of women in philosophy journals prompted some debate in the philosophy blogosphere last week. The paper found women to be underrepresented across a range of prominent journals, yet overrepresented in the two journals studied where review was non-anonymous.
Commenters over at Daily Nous complained about the lack of base-rate data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy for Dummies, Part 6: Obtusity</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-6---obtusity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-6---obtusity/</guid>
      <description>Last time we saw that the set of probability assignments is convex. Today we&amp;rsquo;re going to show that convex sets have a special sort of &amp;ldquo;obtuse&amp;rdquo; relationship with outsiders. Given a point outside a convex set, there is always a point in the set that forms a right-or-obtuse angle with it.
Recall our 2D diagram from the first post. The convex set of interest here is the diagonal line segment from $(0,1)$ to $(1,0)$:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy for Dummies, Part 5: Convexity</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-5---convexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 10:35:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-5---convexity/</guid>
      <description>In this and the next two posts we&amp;rsquo;ll establish the central theorem of the accuracy framework. We&amp;rsquo;ll show that the laws of probability are specially suited to the pursuit of accuracy, measured in Brier distance.
We showed this for cases with two possible outcomes, like a coin toss, way back in the first post of this series. A simple, two-dimensional diagram was all we really needed for that argument. To see how the same idea extends to any number of dimensions, we need to generalize the key ingredients of that reasoning to $n$ dimensions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journals as Ratings Agencies</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/journals-as-ratings-agencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 15:27:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/journals-as-ratings-agencies/</guid>
      <description>Starting in July, philosophy&amp;rsquo;s two most prestigious journals won&amp;rsquo;t reject submitted papers anymore. Instead they&amp;rsquo;ll &amp;ldquo;grade&amp;rdquo; every submission, assigning a rating on the familiar letter-grade scale (A+, A, A-, B+, B, B-, etc.).
They will, in effect, become ratings agencies.
They&amp;rsquo;ll still publish papers. Those rated A- or higher can be published in the journal, if the authors want. Or they can seek another venue, if they think they can do better.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy for Dummies, Part 4: Euclid in the Round</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-4/</guid>
      <description>Last time we took Brier distance beyond two dimensions. We showed that it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;proper&amp;rdquo; in any finite number of dimensions. Today we&amp;rsquo;ll show that Euclidean distance is &amp;ldquo;improper&amp;rdquo; in any finite number dimensions.
When I first sat down to write this post, I had in mind a straightforward generalization of our previous result for Euclidean distance in two dimensions. And I figured it would be easy to prove.
Not so.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Editorial Gravity</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/editorial-gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 10:44:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/editorial-gravity/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ve all been there. One referee is positive, the other negative, and the editor decides to reject the submission.
I&amp;rsquo;ve heard it said editors tend to be conservative given the recommendations of their referees. And that jibes with my experience as an author.
So is there anything to it&amp;mdash;is &amp;ldquo;editorial gravity&amp;rdquo; a real thing? And if it is, how strong is its pull? Is there some magic function editors use to compute their decision based on the referees&amp;rsquo; recommendations?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender &amp; Journal Referees</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/referee-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 09:34:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/referee-gender/</guid>
      <description>We looked at author gender in a previous post, today let&amp;rsquo;s consider referees. Does their gender have any predictive value?
Once again our discussion only covers men and women because we don&amp;rsquo;t have the data to support a deeper analysis.1
Using data from Ergo, we&amp;rsquo;ll consider the following questions:
 Requests. How are requests to referee distributed between men and women? Are men more likely to be invited, for example?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Defense of Reviewer 2</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/reviewer-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 10:36:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/reviewer-2/</guid>
      <description>Spare a thought for Reviewer 2, that much-maligned shade of academe. There&amp;rsquo;s even a hashtag dedicated to the joke:
A rare glimpse of reviewer 2, seen here in their natural habitat pic.twitter.com/lpT1BVhDCX
&amp;mdash; Aidan McGlynn (@AidanMcGlynn) January 15, 2017 
But is it just a joke? Order could easily matter here.
Referees invited later weren&amp;rsquo;t the editor&amp;rsquo;s first choice, after all. Maybe they&amp;rsquo;re less competent, less likely to appreciate your brilliant insights as an author.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy for Dummies, Part 3: Beyond the Second Dimension</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-3/</guid>
      <description>Last time we saw why accuracy-mavens prefer Brier distance to Euclidean distance. But we did everything in two dimensions. That&amp;rsquo;s fine for a coin toss, with only two possibilities. But what if there are three doors and one of them has a prize behind it??
Don&amp;rsquo;t panic! Today we&amp;rsquo;re going to verify that Brier distance is still a proper way of measuring inaccuracy, even when there are more than two possibilities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender &amp; Journal Submissions</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/author-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 10:36:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/author-gender/</guid>
      <description>Does an author&amp;rsquo;s gender affect the fate of their submission to an academic journal? It&amp;rsquo;s a big question, even if we restrict ourselves to philosophy journals.
But we can make a start by using Ergo as one data-point. I&amp;rsquo;ll examine two questions:
 Question 1: Does gender affect the decision rendered at Ergo? Are men more likely to have their papers accepted, for example?
 Question 2: Does gender affect time-to-decision at Ergo?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy for Dummies, Part 2: from Euclid to Brier</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-2/</guid>
      <description>Last time we saw that Euclidean distance is an &amp;ldquo;unstable&amp;rdquo; way of measuring inaccuracy. Given one assignment of probabilities, you&amp;rsquo;ll expect some other assignment to be more accurate (unless the first assignment is either perfectly certain or perfectly uncertain).
That&amp;rsquo;s why accuraticians don&amp;rsquo;t use good ol&amp;rsquo; Euclidean distance.
Instead they use&amp;hellip; well, there are lots of alternatives. But the closest thing to a standard one is Brier distance: the square of Euclidean distance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Thursday Conundrum</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/the-thursday-conundrum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 10:14:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/the-thursday-conundrum/</guid>
      <description>In an earlier post we saw that Mondays and Thursdays are good for editors, at least at Ergo. Potential referees say yes more often when invited on these days. But why?
Mondays aren&amp;rsquo;t too puzzling. It&amp;rsquo;s the start of a new week, so people are fresh, and maybe just a little deluded about how productive the coming week will prove to be.
But Thursdays? They don&amp;rsquo;t seem especially special. I tried speculating a priori about what might be going on there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy for Dummies, Part 1: Euclid Improper</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 09:53:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/accuracy-for-dummies---part-1/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve bumped into the accuracy framework before, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably seen a diagram like this one:
The vertices $(1,0)$ and $(0,1)$ represent two possibilities, whether a coin lands heads or tails in this example.
According to the laws of probability, the probability of heads and of tails must add up to $1$, like $.3 + .7$ or $.5 + .5$. So the diagonal line connecting the two vertices covers all the possible probability assignments&amp;hellip; $(0,1)$, $(.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Editor&#39;s Favourite Days of the Week</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/an-editors-favourite-days/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 10:13:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/an-editors-favourite-days/</guid>
      <description>Finding willing referees is one of the biggest challenges for a journal editor. Are referees more willing some days of the week than others? Apparently they are, on Mondays&amp;hellip; and Thursdays, for some reason. At least, that&amp;rsquo;s how things have gone at Ergo the last couple years (2015 and 2016).
Data Consider the &amp;ldquo;bounce rate&amp;rdquo; for a given day of the week: the portion of invites sent on that day that end up being declined (bounce rate = #declined / #invited).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Victor: Hugo</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 00:00:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/hugo/</guid>
      <description>I chose Hugo to manage this site mainly because it&amp;rsquo;s shiny and new. But there were some substantive reasons, too.
Hugo is famously fast&amp;mdash;really fast&amp;mdash;but that wasn&amp;rsquo;t the big draw for me. For a personal website, even one with many years&amp;rsquo; worth of blogging accrued, Hugo&amp;rsquo;s speed just isn&amp;rsquo;t that important. Quoth the Code Barbarian:
 being the fastest static site generator is like being the resturaunt with the cleanest bathroom: sure, I prefer a faster generator, but I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t pick one generator over another because one shaves off 100ms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iTerm from RStudio</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/iterm-with-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/iterm-with-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>I can&amp;rsquo;t abide OS X&amp;rsquo;s built-in Terminal.app&amp;mdash;too janky by half. So like any reasonable obssessive, I use iTerm2.
Now, RStudio helpfully provides a menu item for opening a shell in the current project&amp;rsquo;s directory. But it calls Terminal.app, with no option to substitue an alternative.
R-bloggers has a helpful post about this. But it&amp;rsquo;s from way back in the dark ages (January 2014), and the solution there doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to work any more thanks to changes in iTerm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This Must Be the Place</title>
      <link>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/this-must-be-the-place/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanweisberg.org/post/this-must-be-the-place/</guid>
      <description>For years I lovingly hand-coded my personal website. The ethos was pure, the product normcore: a single page, packed with links to my academic papers and other projects, all lightly seasoned with a sprinkle of explanatory text.
I scoffed at the polished and capacious WordPress sites of my colleagues. &amp;ldquo;A navbar? With four sections?? Does that link to a PDF of your CV really need a whole page to itself?&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>